Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002 RL.00605
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002, 287 videocassettes
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): The 48th Independence Day Celebration, January 1996, NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (2 copies) (Box 287, Video-cassette BU049)
    Opening remarks were made by U Aung Shwe. He summarized the struggle for independence led by Bogyoke Aung San and the pledges of NLD. He said only the birth of a genuine democracy will solve all the human misery in Burma.
    There was a dance Interval from Mandalay. U Nyunt Yi's (Sagaing) solo classic with Saun (We have lost our land and pride). A group from Myang Mya, a chorus,a duet ("Oo Wayh"), a solo ("For the Sake of Freedom," a tribute to Bo Te Za ), Music "Haven," a number Sagaing ("Doe Na Ga Ni"), and U Aung Khin("Our Mother Land").
    (Leader of the parade.)
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Papalay Anyaint, the 48th Independence day, NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (Box 287, Video-cassette BU050)
    The performance of the popular Papa Lay, Formerly Party Lay. "That is win win situation - the Courage, the Democracy Anyaint(Forbidden by the State Law and Order Restoration Council [SLORC]). When I leave this compound I listen to the news on the corruption in Socialist party...The people's power is my power."
    In the performance, the present situation in Burma was presented in a humorous way.
    Aung San Suu Kyi's speech: "Thanks for the courage of the comedian."
    Program continued.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Weekend Speeches of Aung San Suu Kyi (May 10, 16 and 17, 1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (2 copies) (Box 305, Video-cassette BU051)
    Produced by: NLD Information, Rangoon
    Agrarian programs of State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) on minority, devaluation and inflation, the NLD party procedure, the political pressures and challenges, loopholes in SLORC administration, self encouragement and courage, fear and relief. should be solved wisely. Hatred is destructive, we shall not have them. Love and courage are always together. Unity should be called for."
    U Tin Oo made an apology to Aung San Suu Kyi: "It is good to correct your mistakes and respect historical facts. Dialogue is always welcome. We counter forced relocation and forced labor. We should discuss aspects of democracy. Uneasy smile doesn't mean agreeing."
    Suu Kyi talked about relocation of cemeteries, the present education system, family values, the democracy struggle, the common interest value, moral courage, virtualstarvation in the country.Suu Kyi: "Building the nation with love and affection, not with an iron fist."
    On Oct 8, 1995: Suu Kyi talked about respecting elders, moral discipline, lottery, security in life, alcoholism in Burma and journalistic restrictions.
    The "Truth Forum."
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Weekend Speeches of Aung San Suu Kyi (September 10, 16, 17, 1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 305, Video-cassette BU052)
    Sept 10, 1995: U Tin Oo and U Kyi Maung were present.
    The question and answer section was to counter the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC)'s accusation of her talking nonsense over the fence.
    Question about is the Army for the country or is the country for the army. Suu Kyi referred to her father, saying that leadership should have love and honesty. People should have to right to select their leaders. Development and democracy are not enemies.
    SLORC sponsored the activities of the youth.
    U Tin Oo: I am proud to stand by Aung San Suu Kyi for the cause of democracy. People should have the right to elect and remove leaders.
    U Kyi Maung speaks about examples of the educated men, U Thant and U Soe Nyunt.
    Final remark by Aung San Suu Kyi.
    Sept 16, 1995: Questions such as "What are you doing to achieve the goal?" Suu Kyi talked about freedom of speech, Burmese workers in foreign lands, and the importance of education and technical know how. She said depending too much on power is lack of self-reliance.Modern colonialism is nonsense.
    De Facto and De Jure talked about public servants, habitualized corruption, the National Day celebration, the National convention and constitution, the rule of law of the government and the value of literature.
    Sept 17, 1995,Aung San Suu KyiandU Tin Oo
    They speak about the present economic status, the lack of appropriate systems, the SLORC failure to appreciate the traditional way, the matter of celebrations, the government controlled media and the local production, urging people to use locally made products.
    "The ultimate answer is Democracy."
    They also talked about the judicial system under democracy, saying democracy will allow everyone to work for the country.
    U Tin Oo: "We are willing to give everythingfor democracy."
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Weekend Speeches by Aung San Su Kyi (September 23, 24, 30, 1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 304 and 305, Video-cassette BU053)
    September 23, 1995:
    Aung San Suu Kyi speaks about the hardship of the grass roots level, and the living standard of the general public. U Aung San's democracy philosophy: "True democratic government is not only elected by people but has to work to guarantee the economic equitability in the country - equal opportunity."
    She speaks about the mercenaries injournalism and asks the public to ignore the trash publications.
    "Leaders must understand the public. We don't want power. We only want democracy. Power is from the people. Time will tell who tells the truth. The lack of press freedom causes the spread of rumor."
    She recalled student's chapters in history of Burma. "We will rebuild the student union building." She states that economic gaps cause civil disorder. The State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) sponsored organizations are those in which greed overcomes honesty. Giving bribes is an insult. Don't sell off your morality.
    She explained democracy within the context of Burma.
    Sept 24: Aung San Suu Kyi, U koi Maung and U Tin Oo
    Aung San Suu Kyi speaks about drug problem in Burma. She proposed alternate approach and the UN Declaration on Human Rights.
    She speaks about present situation on education and criticized the tea money phenomenon. She speaks also about the SLORC tax and the unequal distribution of resources.
    U Tin Oo commented on Buddhism-based politicalsystem, historical lessons, global struggle againstabsolute monarch, human rights. "Human rights will be guaranteed only when we have democracy. "He compared and commented on ten ancient rules of kings and modern democracy.
    U Kyi Maung about a movie "Oshin,"and the miracle in Japan.
    Sept. 30: Suu Kyi on the memory of U Aung San in people's hearts, SLORC's progress, forced porters in Burma, culture and dollar value, national progress, education for the public, general characteristics ofthe public and the literature restrictions and censorship.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Weekend speeches by Aung San Suu Kyi (January 13 and 14, 1996), NTSC VHS [TRT 0:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 304, Video-cassette BU054)
    Jan. 13, 1996:
    Suu Kyi encourages people to be courageous and ready for the reconstruction. She speaks about the present agrarian situation, State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC)'s ambition, the dry season cropping, the political system, the national unity, the definition of heroes, and profit taking.
    "Leaders must have courage to acknowledge the existence of the problems."
    She also talked about the forced labor issue, the people's misery, the definition of the Least Developed Nations. "The saddest part was undermining our strength. Educated persons never supportdictatorship. We should be capable of abiding the law. My father founded the army and I never hated it."
    Jan 14, 1996: U Kyi Maung, U Tin Oo andAung San Suu Kyi.
    Ethnic insurgencies the cause of colonialism?
    They discuss the strength of the country. "We all have to defend our independence, personal freedom. We need to work on these thoughtfully, but we will have to work with risks. "They discussed also thefailureof SLORC and people's lack of confidence in them. "SLORC's plan to rule is an insult to the entire Burmese population."
    U Tin Oo talked about individual freedom, the law, Provision 102 /103 on the arrests. "Democracy is the people's will and nothing can be taken away from us."
    U Kyi Maung discussed issues from the capitalist democracy to capitalistic wars, the overall economy and inflation, and some significant leaders in the financial world.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Aung San Suu Kyi Public Speeches, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 304, Video-cassette BU055)
    U Tin Oo and U Kyi Maung were seen.
    Suu Kyi answered questions on the responsibility of the army and the people, and about courage, politicians, and a successful economy.
    U Tin Oo and U Kyi Maung both spoke.
  - Images Asia: Aung San Suu Kyi Speech for UN Commission on Human Rights, NTSC VHS [TRT 0:11:00] (2 copies) (Box 304, Video-cassette BU056)
    Opening remark: National League for Democracy (NLD) members are harassed. Human rights is a universal element. Rule of law is a concept of peace. There is no Rule of Law in Burma. We should appeal to the international community to take greater interest in the restoration of democracy in Burma. NLD wrote to State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) about five instances of human rights violations. Two duties of NLD: protest lawlessness of SLORC and implementation of UN Resolution.Concrete steps should be taken to fulfill people's will. Economic progress can not be guaranteed without the rule of law. We have called trying to establish dialogues but SLORC chose to ignore. The situation in Burma is threatening regional stability.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): ASSK Extends Respect to the Elderly (October 8, 1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (2 copies) (Box 304, Video-cassette BU057)
    Produced by: NLD Rangoon
    In the NLD compound, the elders are on the stage and the rest are on the ground. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) was invited but declined to attend. There were traditional candle lightings and bowing. People introduced themselves one by one, gifts were distributed and the elder people were happy.
    "Democracy cannot be built with the power of the arm, but only by the power of wisdom. You won't know politics without learning history. If you want human rights you have to have your integrity," said Aung San Suu Kyi in the closing remarks. "We must know what is good and must appreciate what is bad."
    Aung San Suu Kyi mingled with the crowd.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Aung San Suu Kyi with Kachin Leaders (August 31, 1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:2:00] (2 copies) (Box 304, Video-cassette BU058)
    Aung San Suu Kyi's compound.
    Each delegation spoke out openly. They submitted their support to NLD and Aung San Suu Kyi. There was a question about the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC)'s claim on economic growth.
    A poem was read by Kachin Hill - Aung San's blood.
    Leaders answered questions. Suu Kyi said trust is important in national reconciliation. She praised brave individuals.
  - Independent Production: Classes Dismissed, Future Denied, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:12:00] (2 copies) (Box 304, Video-cassette BU059)
    Produced by: Campaign Committee for Open Schools World View Rights
    The future education of the children of Burma is uncertain. Children are caught in the civil war. Over 100,000 children do not go to school to get basic education. Colleges have been closed for a long time.
    Lin Lin Tun: "The Regime is worried all the time."
    Story of illegal migrant workers in Burma.
    Teacher Ma Ma told Daw Suu Kyi, "The kin of the Army study a different system."
    Jase Ramos Horta: "This is a crime to shut down schools."
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): ASSK with Irrawaddy Delta leaders, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (Box 304, Video-cassette BU060)
    Busloads of delegation members arrive. Enthusiastic faces shown. The Pinne and Kachin NLD outfit, Doe Nagani, are seen getting off the buses. A rollcall is made and they enter the gates of the NLD Headquarters.
    Ceremony begins as Suu Kyi and U Tin Oo enter.
    U Tin Oo originally came from the Irrawaddy region. "We must now do everything we can to let our children enjoy freedom."
    Township matters are discussed. The delegation expresses overwhelming support for the NLD. Thirty-two of them are elected members of parliament. Their commitment is still strong in spite of the relentless harassment of State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).
    The delegation discusses many other issues: Young people mischievously vandalize SLORC's infrastructure but NLD members suffer the consequences.
    The forced labor situation is still bad. Farmers areforced to give their crops to the government. They cite the failure of SLORC's initiatives, such as the dry-season rice experiment.
    Aung San Suu Kyi extends a brief theory of democracy. She says that people's consent should be required in the government projects. Problems will always be there but the democratic approach to solutions is the most productive way.
    Economy and education are discussed. She continues: "Now is the time for everyone to put their best efforts forward for democracy. It will be a rough road to democracy though."
    She speaks of the courage of the young people, the politics and comments on severe punishment for the failure to fulfill the quota.
    U Tin Oo also responded to the conversations.
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi's weekend speech is heard.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Aung San Suu Kyi meets NLD leadership and Moulmein delegates at Mon State (August 25, 1995), NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (Box 304, Video-cassette BU061)
    After a roll call, people enter hall. Pamelo presents gift to Suu Kye.
    They speak about harassment, about the few township offices remaining. Suu Kyi gives a brief lecture on democratic aspects. She uses the example of South Africa. She says that money can't buy anything. She encourages people. She comments negatively on superstitious way of life such as the dependence on fortune tellers. She also comments on the democratic spirit and political power.
    "I cannot let my work suffer for my personal security. If unity prevails it will not take long for democracy and freedom to come."
  - Earth Action Group: Protest against Union Oil Company of California (Unocal) (December 12, 1996), NTSC VHS [TRT 01:03:00] (2 copies) (Box 304 and 306, Video-cassette BU062)
    Produced by: Earth Action Group, LA
    This is by Burma Forum LA. The Earth Action Group and various environmental and human rights groups are seen. Unocal signed an agreement that condemned Burmese military regime State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) to build controversial Yadana pipeline.
    It was a rainy day. Detailed actions were taken in front of Unocal headquarters Los Angeles. Activists tied themselves to the Unocal gas delivery truck. Khin Maung Shwe, Taw Myo Myint and Ko Latt, and Adriana chained themselves to the truck. Climbers climbed the tank and placed a huge banner on top saying: "TORTURE IN BURMA; HEROIN IN the USA. BOYCOTT Unocal." Maung and Taw shout: "Boycott Unocal! Unocal out of Burma!" Haley, little Htet Htet joined Maung and Shwe. "No slave child labor in Burma. No pipeline project now!"
    Khin Maung Soe "I am a follower of our leader, Aung San Suu Kyi. I was jailed and tortured for two years.I am an NLD member."
    Tin Maung Aye: "Stop child labor. Do us a favor."
    "We are willing to go to jail. For my people and my country." Sai Hla Pe.
    LA Police and Fire Department arrived. "Shame on Unocal." Workers responded with peace symbol. Kyaw Moe Zaw, the Los Angeles Police Department and Fire Department peacefully ended and scores of people were arrested.
  - Amateur Footage: Interview with Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, NTSC VHS [TRT 0o:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 306, Video-cassette BU063)
    Produced by: Nancy Anderson
    Freedom in Burma is costly but very precious. Interview conducted by Nancy Anderson.
  - Asia Now: News from Burma TV, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:45:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU064)
    Produced by: Asia Now
    Edited news report.
    Downtown Rangoon, Aung San Suu Kyi had her weekend speech.
    Sein Win recorded and distributed scripts among supporters. San Gnwe was a lawyer who wanted to write story. He met with Suu Kyi. "I am optimistic. We will certainly achieve our goal. The military does not have popular support."
  - Burma Forum: Fight for Freedom and Human Rights in Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:25:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU066)
    Produced by: Burma Forum, Los Angeles
    Edited report by Burma Forum Los Angeles.
    Kevin Rudigers gives a brief history of Burma's story - Army crushed democratic movement, killing 6000 people.
    Aung San Suu Kyi: "Authorities set aside the result of election, but they will not last for long because this is the will of the people."
    Suu Kyi talked about the acts committed by the Army: porters, army recruits, forced labor, burned villages, burned churches, animal skeletons all over the land, the body of Paddy, Saw Hla Htoo signs of atrocities,people dying of easily treatable diseases.
    Foreign investors are welcome in Burma. Companies put blind eyes to the suffering of the people, Katherine Redford said, since foreign investors come in, the general situation has worsened. Extensive consumer boycott campaign resulted in massive withdrawal of a lot of companies but some stubbornly remained.
    The LA Free Burma Ordinance 1998 was supported by over 100 groups.
  - ISBA: National League for Democracy (NLD) CEO Meeting(in Burmese), NTSC VHS [TRT 01:33:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU067)
    Produced by: ISBA
    July 17, 2000, by ISBDA
    Burma's Democracy and Our Future
    NLD's activities. NLD Logo, red bases, yellow peacock and a star.
    The first meeting with the national representatives after Suu Kyi's release, in her home - the NLD headquarters. Delegates were lined-up to meet the leaders. There was background music, "Victory for Burma." Aung San Suu Kyi, U Aung Shwe and U Tin Oo were present.
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi began the ceremony: "Unity is key.Dialogue is our way so please support us. I don't hate soldiers. My father was one. The way to democracy will be a long and hard road. I don't want to make promises that I may not be able to keep. I have a duty to work and suffer. I work for the futureand learn from the past. Hatred is always related to fear. I can face death because what I have done is not wrong. We don't disown anyone, including the exiled students. I am not doing anything secretly. I just listen to VOA, BBC and DVB.
    Delegates left the compound.
    People promised their full support. People say: "We don't want you to die before the work is done."
    Huge crowd gathered around Suu Kyi's home.
  - ITN: Inside Burma - Land of Fear, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:50:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU068)
    Produced by: John Pilger/Bull Frog
    Network: ITN
    Report by John Pilger on Burma's "harsh, bloody, and uncompromising" regime.
    John Pilger: "More than a million people have been forced from their homes and, according to the UN, untold thousands have been massacred, tortured and subjected to a modern form of slavery. 'Burma, says Amnesty International, is a prison without bars.'"
    According to Pilger, the filming for this documentary was done in secret as the regime attempted to cover its crimes with the help of foreign investors and by declaring 1996 the year of the tourist.
    Interviews include: Burmese exiles, refugees, National League for Democracy (NLD) leader Aung San Suu Kyi, Dr. Aung Kin (Burma Historian), foreign investor James Sherwood, and Dr. Martin Morland (Ex. U.N. Ambassador to Burma).
    The Inya Lake massacre - the site where the March 16, 1988 student demonstration took place.Pilger: "According to eyewitnesses, the soldiers beat many of them to death, singling out the girls. Those who escaped were pursued here into the lake, where they were caught and drowned one by one. Of the survivors, 42 were locked into a waiting van and left in the noon-day heat where all of them suffocated to death. In the meantime fire engines were brought in to wash away the blood."
    Rare camera appearance of Ne Win giving a speech. New Win: "If there are more demonstrations, the army will shoot to kill."
    Testimonies on the building of the railway that will transport soldiers and supplies to an area where a billion dollar gas line is being built for the French oil company Total -- owned by the French government and the US company Unocal. Footage of children being used to construct the site.
    Scenes of children used as laborers, carrying clumps of clay on their heads. Pilger: "Children are also forced to make bricks for the army, and that construction is being done to attract tourists."
    Interview with James Sherwhood, Chairman of Orient Express Hotels, Road to Mandalay River Cruises. He claims that there is no proof that there are human rights violations in Burma. He claims that he consulted with the CIA who told him that the allegations were not true. He says that it is "untactful" to contact the "opposition leader" Aung San Suu Kyi. He met only with the generals.
    Pilger claims that the Burmese government receives money from foreign investors - mainly gas companies. British company also traded arms with the government. United States, Japan, and Australian companies also trade with Burma. NHK, a Japanese media organization, told the filmmakers of this documentary that they cannot share the footage of soldiers killing civilians because it is "too delicate and might threaten Myanmar's stability. Please erase the materials from your library. I appreciate you understanding the situation."
    Scenes of Karen ethnic minorities who have escaped to Thailand.
  - TV Myanmar: News Clips, 1994, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU069)
    News Clips from TV Myanmar, Sept 9, 1995,in Burmese Language.
    Khin Nyunt indirectly criticized National League for Democracy (NLD), boasted about national convention, increasing foreign investments. He criticized some countries who pressured State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).
    The second anniversary of USDA: Unity, Solidarity and Development Association.
    Diamond Jubilee, Memorial Hall, Rangoon University earth-breaking ceremony, Chaung guat Dam Pyobwe Town, the opening ceremony by Tin Oo Secretary II, sugar cane production facility in Pyinmana, cotton production fields, underground water utilization facilities and development projects.
    Madeleine Albright in Rangoon.
    Tourist Festival in 1996.
  - TV Myanmar: News Clips, 1995, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:60:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU070)
    Sept 10, 1995 Tin Oo's activities (in Burmese).
    Visiting the Buddhist temple construction site.
    Visiting the Dau Pone's road construction.
    Participating in the Unity, Solidarity and Development Association (USDA) Tin Oo Thingan Gyun Anniversary.
    Visiting Nhinsigone - Home of the aged, and attended the alms-giving ceremony.
    Attending the Haling Computer Room opening ceremony.
    Delegates arrive to attend the second anniversary of USDA.
    Attending the Diamond Jubilee students' meeting.
    The USDA Boss visited an oil well with Minister K Maung Thein.
  - Bared Face Production: Life on the Line, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:39:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU071)
    Produced by: Bared Face Production
    Airing Program: Channel 4, Great Britain